A Guide to the Papers of James Fenimore Cooper, 1794-1943, n.d.
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of James Fenimore Cooper, 1794-1943, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6245-k
This collection consists of 58 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This was a gift to the library on 4 December 1974.
Scope and Content Information
This collection of the additional papers of James Fenimore Cooper includes manuscripts, letters, engravings, prints, letters, notes, clippings and miscellaneous items.
Contents List
- Bound Volume 1827-1849, 9 items, bound in blue volume
  - Letter from Cooper to Mr. [Gosselin?] 8 September 1827, ALS, 1 page.
    Cooper to Mr. [Gosselin?](French publisher), with drawing of "Templeton" (i.e., Cooperstown as it should be in Red Rover.
    This is not found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper.
    .
  - Letter from Cooper to "My Dear Little (Sarah Heyward Cruger) Saidee" 18 July 1849, ALS, 2 pages.
    Cooper to Sarah Heywood Cruger, regarding daguerreotype (of his son?).
    This is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper, Volume VI, 54.
  - Letter from Cooper to "My Dear Little Saidee" September 10 - October 6 1849, ALS, 3 pages, with typescript copy.
    Cooper to "My Dear Litte Saidee," regarding social and family affairs.
    This is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper, Volume VI, 70.
  - Print of Cooper n.d., Print
    Print of Cooper, engraved by W.E. Marshall
  - Engraving of Cooper n.d.
    Engraving of Cooper, house at bottom of engraving
  - Engraving n.d., Engraving
    The author of The Spy, by Thomson, missing 3/27/75. In place of this there is an engraving of Cooper "from the original painting of Chapel...1861."
  - Engraving n.d., Engraving
    Engraving, "J. Fenimore Cooper," by J.C. Buttre
  - Poem n.d., AMS, 1 page, with typescript
    Poem, begins "and this goes to Saidee."
    This is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper, Volume IV, 54.
  - Print of Otsego Hall n.d., Print
- Letters 1794-1943
  - William Cooper Letter 6 March 1794, ALS, 1 page.
    William Cooper (father of novelist), regarding mortgage.
  - Letter from John Jay to James F. Cooper 10 September 1821, ALS, 2 pages, with AMS, biographical sketch on same leaf.
    John Jay to James F. Cooper.
    This item is not found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper.
  - Letter from Cooper to Mr. [Gosselin?] 8 September 1827, ALS, 1 page, in bound volume.
  - Letter from Cooper to Messrs. Carey, Lea, and Carey 12 December 1827, ALS, 1 page.
    Cooper to Messrs. Carey, Lea, and Carey regarding Red Rover, mentions Bradish.
  - Letter from Cooper to M. Bossange [10 January?] 1828, ALS, 1 page.
    Cooper to M. Bossange, sending him apples grown in America.
  - Cooper to Sutherland Douglas 30 March 1830, ALS, 1 page.
    Invitation.
  - Letter from Cooper to Colonel Aspinwall 1832, ALS, 1 page
  - Letter from Cooper to George Tyler Bigelow 28 August 1837, ALS, 1 page.
    Cooper to Geroge Tyler Bigelow, refusing an invitation to address the Boston Lyceum. Mentions Mr. Everett.
    This is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper, Volume III, 285.
  - Letter from Cooper to J. De P.Ogden 30 January 1830, ALS, 2 pages, with typewritten copy.
    Cooper to J. De P.Ogden, legal affairs (involving Ketchum and Comstock). Mentions work on the "History."
    This is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper, Volume III, 365.
  - Letter from Cooper to J. De.Ogden 22 August 1839, ALS, 1 page.
    Cooper to J. De P.Ogden, regarding Ketchum and Comstock legal affairs, English Economy.
  - Letter from Cooper to William P. Jones 12 December 1845, ALS, 1 page.
    Cooper to William P. Jones, regarding the cherubs (scuplture) by Greenough.
    This is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper, Volume V, 109.
  - Letter from Cooper to "My Dear Little Saidee" 18 July 1849, ALS, 2 pages, in bound volume.
  - Letter from Cooper to "My Dear Little Saidee" 10 September - 6 October 1849, ALS, 3 pages, in bound volume.
  - Letter from Cooper to Horatio Greenough 10 September 1849, ALS, 1 page
    Cooper to Horatio Greenough, introduction for Judge Denis, family affairs. "I weigh 200, look young for sixty, and feel like a boy."
  - Letter from Cooper to Gen. Thomas McCall Cadwalader [4-7 March 1850 ?], ALS, 1 page.
    Cooper to Gen. Thomas McCall Cadwalader, invitation.
    This is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper, Volume VI, 152.
  - Letter from Cooper to Dr. Freeborn Garrison Thralle 3 November 1850
    Cooper to Dr. Freeborn, thanking him for services to Mrs. Cooper.
    This is found in James Franklin Beard's Letters and Journals of James Fenimore Cooper, Volume VI, 230.
  - Susan F. Cooper to Miss Jay 28 July 1851, ALS, 4 pages.
    Susan F. Cooper to Miss Jay, lengthy description of J.F.C.'s illness, his confirmation in church, Christitan beliefs. Two months before death.
  - Letter from Susan F. Cooper to... 26 January 1857, ALS, 1 page.
    Susan F. Cooper to..., obituary (newspsper) of Susan
  - Susan F. Cooper to... 26 January 1857[9?], ALS, 1 page.
  - Letter from Susan F. Cooper to Eliza 3 February 1857, ALS, 2 pages
  - Letter from Susan F. Cooper to Gentlemen 1 November 1858, ALS, 1 page.
  - Susan F. Cooper to Commodore William [Crawford?] [Shubrick?] 26 April 1860
  - Letter from Susan F. Cooper to Commodore Shubrick 7 December 1860, ALS, 1 page.
  - Susan F. Cooper to Sarah 11 March 1864, ALS, 1 page.
  - Letter from Susan F. Cooper to... 2 June 1869, ALS, 1 page.
  - Letter from Susan F. Cooper to... 8 September 1869, ALS, 1 page.
  - Letter from Susan F. Cooper to [W.W. Cooper] 8 August 1871, ALS, 2 pages.
    Susan F. Cooper to [W.W. Cooper], geneology.
  - Letter from Susan F. Cooper to [W.W. Cooper] 30 March 1872, ALS, 4 pages.
    Susan F. Cooper to [W.W. Cooper], regarding her grandfather.
  - Paul F. Cooper to W.W. Cooper 4 May 1872, ALS, 4 pages.
    PAul F. Cooper to W.W. Cooper, geneology
  - Letter from Susan F. Cooper to... 7 October 1872, ALS, 2 pages
  - Letter from Susan. F. Cooper to [W.W. Cooper] 21 October 1873, ALS, 4 pages.
  - Letter from Susan F. Cooper to [W.W. Cooper] 16 October 1875, ALS, 4 pages.
    Susan F. Cooper to [W.W. Cooper], regarding edition of J.F.C.'s works.
  - Letter from Susan F. Cooper to [W.W. Cooper] 2 October 1872, ALS, 3 pages
  - Letter from Isaac Cooper to W.W. Cooper 1 December 1879, ALS, 3 pages.
  - F.O. Darley to... 19 October 1884, ALS, 5 pages, with typed copy.
  - Letter from Susan F. Cooper to "My Dear Madam" 22 October 1855, ALS, 3 pages
  - Susan F. Cooper to "My Young Friend" 17 February 1886, ALS, 2 pages, enclosure.
    Susan F. Cooper to "My Young Friend," containing enclosure with strip of paper bearing Cooper's handwriting, from Chapter VII of unidentified Ms re demoisell (Bartoris?).
  - Letter from Susan F. Cooper to Mr. Foot 26 January 1893, ALS, 3 pages
  - Letter from James F. Cooper (not novelist) to Will 12 June 1926, ALS, 1 page
  - Letter from James F. Cooper (not novelist) to Mrs. Davis 12 June 1926, ALS, 2 pages
  - Letter from James F. Cooer (not novelist) to Capt. Pleadwell 12 June 1926, ALS, with envelope, 2 pages.
  - Letter from A.L. Beecher to Maj. A.D. Fille 24 September 1943, ALS, with envelope, 1 page
  - Letter from Susan F. Cooper to Mlle. H. Boissard n.d., ALS, 2 pages, in French.
  - Letter from James F. Cooper to William Sotheby n.d., ANS, 1 page, in 3rd person
    James F. Cooper to William Sotheby, an invitation.
  - Letter from Cooper to Corbin n.d., LS, with typewritten copy, 1 page
- Documents 1838-1850
  - Document signed by Cooper 9 July 1838, Check, enclosure, 1 page
    Document signed by Cooper, with brief biographical newspaper clipping enclosed.
  - Document signed by Cooper 12 May 1843, Check
    Check signed by Cooper, for $10.00
  - Document signed by Cooper July 1850, Receipt
    Receipt signed by Cooper, for $50.00
- Clipping from New York Times Magazine12 September 1926, Newspaper Clipping